<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Further and more true account of the apprehending and taking of Gerard Dremelius the Drawer, for the murther of Oliver Norris Esquire, at the White-Cross Tavern in East Smith field, his examination, and confession, together with the examination of Micheal [sic] Van Burgh, and Catherin Truet before the coroners inquest, and their commitment to Newgate on Saturday last. : As also a further, and more particular account of the said barbarous murther.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1700</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 10 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 2 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A85061</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F2551A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R177278</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">45097797</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 45097797</idno>
            <idno type="VID">171383</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A85061)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 171383)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2572:32)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Further and more true account of the apprehending and taking of Gerard Dremelius the Drawer, for the murther of Oliver Norris Esquire, at the White-Cross Tavern in East Smith field, his examination, and confession, together with the examination of Micheal [sic] Van Burgh, and Catherin Truet before the coroners inquest, and their commitment to Newgate on Saturday last. : As also a further, and more particular account of the said barbarous murther.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([2] p.).   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.W. near Fleet-street.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1700.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Dremelius, Gerhard Jurgen, d. 1700.</term>
               <term>Norris, Oliver, d. 1700.</term>
               <term>Truet, Catherine.</term>
               <term>Van Burgh, Michael.</term>
               <term>Murder --  England --  London --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Broadsides --  England --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb facs="tcp:171383:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A further and more true Account of the Apprehending and Taking, of <hi>Gerard Dremelius the Drawer,</hi> For the Murther of Oliver Norris Eſquire, At the White-Groſs Tavern in <hi>Eaſt Smith field,</hi> his Examination, and Confeſſion, together with the Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of <hi>Micheal Van Burgh,</hi> and <hi>Catherin Truet</hi> before the Coroners Inqueſt, and their Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to Newgate on Saturday laſt: As alſo a further, and more particular Account of the ſaid barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Murther.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>GERARD DREMELIUS,</hi> the <hi>Dutch Mans</hi> Drawer, who was chiefly concern'd in the Murther of <hi>Oliver Norris</hi> Eſſ<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> at the <hi>White-Croſs Tavern</hi> in <hi>Eaſt Smith-field</hi> was Diſcover'd and Taken after this manner, <hi>viz.</hi> the Conſtables and other Officers of the Pariſh where the Murther was Committed; having Intelligence, that he carried a Hamper out very early the next Morning, and that he went towards St. <hi>Catherins</hi> with it, they by making Enquire, along the Water ſide, fortunately found out the Water Man that carried him up the the River about 5 of the Clock, that Morning who inform'd them, that he carried his Hamper to Mr. <hi>Taylors</hi> at the <hi>Crown</hi> in <hi>Charles ſtreet</hi> by <hi>St. James</hi>'s <hi>Square;</hi> where being come by the Water<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man's direction, they found that one of the Lord <hi>Shoots</hi> Foot-Men had fetched the ſaid Hamper away, by the ſaid Drawer's order, upon which ſending to the Lord <hi>Shoots</hi> (who is Ambaſſador from the Duke of <hi>Zell)</hi> for the ſaid Foot Man; he told them that the Drawer being his Country Man, and well known in his Lords Family, he had taken a Lodging for him at Mr. <hi>Comins</hi> at the <hi>Cock and Bottle</hi> in the ſame ſtreet, where he left him: But Mr. <hi>Comins,</hi> would not conſent to entertain him, till he had farther enquired of him at the Lord <hi>Shoots</hi> Houſe in St. <hi>James</hi>'s <hi>Square,</hi> where the Servants gave him a favourable Character: Whereupon going thither; they found him up two pare of Staires upon the Bed about 8 in the Evening, where he was Appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended and taken (and not at the <hi>Crown</hi> by St. <hi>James</hi>'s <hi>Square,</hi> as was falſely given out) when being charged with the ſaid Murther, he at firſt utterly deny'd it, alledging he did not forſtand them but being taken thence that Night, and the next Day being <hi>Saturday,</hi> he was carried before the Worſhipful Juſtice <hi>Bateman,</hi> in <hi>Well Colſs,</hi> where the Hamper being opened, they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> all bloody, at which time being Examin'd <hi>he C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nfeſſed that he Murt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ered him, and being asked why? be alledged that the Gentleman drew his Sword againſt him, where upon in his defence (as he ſays) he Knock'd him Down; and having got that advantage, it ſuddaidly came in his mind to Murther him for his Money, which he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> perform'd by dragging him to a Di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>chs ſide behind the old Buildings near his Maſters Houſe, where he cat his Throat with a ſharp Knife of his own, and having Robb'd and Strip'd him, he threw his naked Body into the Ditch, or Common Shore, which was deep of Water and Mudd, laying a conſide<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ble quanty <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f Dirt and Rubbish on him, and having covered the Blood as well as he could, went to his Maſters Houſe, and asked his pretended Miſtreſs for a Hamper, who ſeeing his Hands bloody, asked him how they came ſo, he anſwered, he beleived he had kill'd the Gentleman; ſo ſhe fetch'd him the Hamper, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſent him go<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>idg. This being his real Confeſſion, and no other, Notwithſtanding the flying Reports and Pamphlets, to the contrary, However the Maid being Examin'd, declared that, when ſhe asked her at firſt about the Hamper, ſhe ſaid it was lent to a Sugar-Baker, but before the Juſtice and Corner, Conf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d the Drawer had it, and being found in ſeveral other contrary Tale<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, the Juſtice ordered them to be had before the Gor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners Inqueſt, where the ſame matters was again repeated, without any or very little Variation, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon Mr. George</hi> Rives <hi>Coroner, Committed</hi> Gerard Dreme<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>us <hi>the Drawer, together with</hi> Van Burgh <hi>and his pretended Wife to</hi> Newgate, <hi>where the two former are very much loaded with Irons, in order to be Try'd for the ſaid Murther the next approaching Seſſions, but the Maid is to be Diſcharged upon Bail.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>On <hi>Thurſday</hi> laſt being the 13th of <hi>June</hi> 1700, Mr. <hi>Noris</hi> a Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>et of Horie, belonging to the <hi>Kings-Guards,</hi> having occaſion to go to <hi>Epping</hi> upon ſome weighty Buſineſs, his Father enjoying a very great Eſtate in thoſe parts, took Houſe in order for his Journey that Morning but unfortunately (as I may ſo terme it) he met with ſome Gentlemen of his acquaintange, who being ſomething longer than ordinary in taking their Leaves of him; he was ſo much diſordered in Drink as rendered him uncapable of going his Journey, having Drunk variety of Liquors in St. <hi>Catherins,</hi> that where leaving his Friends, he ſecretly with drew himſelf, and ſent his Horſe; by a Porter to the <hi>Bull-Head</hi> in <hi>White-Chappel,</hi> and at the ſame time took Coach, and came about 10 a Clock that Night to the <hi>White-Croſs Tavern</hi> in <hi>Eaſt Smith-Field,</hi> the Maſter of which, being one <hi>Van Burgh</hi> a <hi>Dutch-Man,</hi> where he continued till after 11 a Clock, being ſeen there by ſeveral of the Neighbours, but was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e
<pb facs="tcp:171383:2" rendition="simple:additions"/> more heard of till next Morning about Seven, at which time was found by a ſtrong Water Man, in a <hi>Maudlins Rents</hi> very near the ſaid <hi>Dutch</hi> Houſe, ſtrip'd ſtark naked and Murthered in a cruel and inhuman manner, having his Throat cut from Ear to Ear, in ſuch a ſavage and abominable manner as ſcarcely ever was known or heard of, for not only his Wind-pipe and all his Throat was cut croſs, but the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joints of his Neck Bones almoſt cut aſunder, with a cruel bruiſe on the left ſide of his Head; and not only ſo but all his Fingers on his right Hand cut overthwart, ſuppoſed to be done by his laying hold of the Knife, which prov'd the tragical in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument of his Death, he likewiſe was barbarouſly hack'd, and mangled on the left Hand and Arm, being Robb'd of all his Cloathes, and a conſiderable qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of Gold and Silver, which his Friends has ſince afirm'd he had about him over Night, ſome ſays 100 Guineas beſides a rich Watch, and other things of great vallue; having nothing on him but, a pair of Boots, and ſcarlet Stockings, which tis ſuppoſed, his Murtherers could not get off with ſuch ſpeed as they deſired.</p>
            <p>The newes of this barbarous Cruelty being nois'd about, abundance of People came crowding from all parts of <hi>London</hi> to ſee this Murthered Object, upon which it appearing by ſeveral that he was late the Night before at the <hi>Dutch Mans</hi> Houſe which was near that place; he and his Wife were taken into Cuſtody on ſuſpition and carried before the Worſhipful Juſtice <hi>Conſtable</hi> in <hi>Goodman-Fields,</hi> where they were ſtrickly Examined, as was alſo his Maid, who all Confeſſed that the deceaſed Gentleman was drinking in his Houſe from 10 of the Clock that Night till after 11 and that <hi>Van Burgh</hi> offered his Man to conduct him to his Lodging, but he refuſing it they alledged that a ſtranger coming by accidentuly, the Gentleman agreed with him for 6 pence to go with him to his Lodging, and that they did not ſeem him any more till Dead the next Morning among the crowd of People; but the Juſtice asking where the Drawer was, his Wife reply'd, they had ſent him to fetch ſome Wine from a certaine place which ſhe named, whereupon a Meſſinger being ſent thither to know the truth, ſoon brought word that he had not been there, which made their Caſe the more Suſpitious, after which the Maid declared that ſhe ſaw the ſame Gentleman, about 10 of the Clock Drinking below Stairs <hi>with the Drawer at which time her Maſter and Miſtrirs cauſed her to go to Bed contrary to her uſual cuſtom, for other Nights ſhe us'd to ſit up lateſt in the Houſe but that Night ſhe was forced to Bed in all the haſt, and further declared that when in her Chamber ſhe heard a ſtrange buſtling Noiſe below inſomuch that ſhe was coming down to ſee what was the matter, but was met by her Miſtreſs, who told her all was well, and ſo ſhe went into her Chamber again and ſo to Bed, but knew nothing further, only ſaw her Miſtreſs fetch down the Hamper, in great haſt towards the Morning, when asking her af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards what was becom'd of it, her anſwer was, ſhe had lent it to a Sugar-Baker, tho ſome hours after ſhe told her who had it, deſiring her not to ſpeak of it, alleding her Life was in her Hand; ſo that altho the Drawer doth yet ſeem to take Fact wholy upon himſelf, yet there is great cauſe to ſuſpect both her, and her pretended Husbands Innocency.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Upon further ſearch of his Body after he was carried in a Coffin to the Conſtables Houſe, ſeveral wounds were found in divers parts of his Body, being uſed after ſuch a Loathſome and Inhuman manner, that the moſt Savage, Barbarous, and worſt of <hi>Infidels</hi> would be aſhamed of. Twas obſerved among other diſcourſe which the <hi>Dutch</hi> Man expreſs'd, during his being in the Conſtables Cuſtody tis ſaid he told them that it was their way in <hi>Holland</hi> when any Perſon was Murthered by a Confederacy they always ſent the Murtherer out of the way, the very inſtant after he had committed it, while the other took care to hide the Murthered Body, and by that means they uſually eſcaped unpuniſhed; and if ſo this was one of his own Countrey Tricks, but tis thought he will meet with contrary ſucceſs here.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. W.</hi> near <hi>Fleet-ſtreet.</hi> 1700.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
